English Legal Documents mss. IV, 1200-1898 LMC 1333
Lilly Library
English Legal Documents mss. IV
1200-1898
Lilly Library
LMC 1333
4 Boxes 1 standard, 3 custom
1 folio oversize
English Legal Documents mss. IV, 1200-1898, consist of those manuscripts concerned with English legal matters which have been acquired as individual pieces.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of manuscripts aquired from various sources regarding English legal matters.
Related Material
See English Legal Documents mss., English Legal Documents mss. II, and English Legal Documents mss. III, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Law; Legal documents
- Folio - [Grant by Henry de Pinkeny at the request of Lettice his wife to Richard, son of Gilbert, of land in Wappenham (in Northamptonshire) for an annual fee of 12 d.]., ca. 1200 -; 1 leaf 12.5 x 20 cm. (Box 1)
  General
  On vellum
  Attached circular equestrian seal in green wax, 6 cm. in diameter.
  Encased in sand-colored box.
  Accompanied by transcription and translation of text as well as Pinkeny family history (and family tree).
  Document description is as follows: "Northamptonshire. Grant by Henry de Pinkeny at the request of Lettice his wife to Richard, son of Gilbert, of land in Wappenham, for an annual rent of 12d., undated, witnessed by Anculph and Thomas de Pinkeny and 12 others. On vellum, 110 by 195 mm., 13 line. Circular equestrian seal (55 mm. diameter) in green wax, edges chipped but a good impression. Preserved in a fitted box. Phillipps Ms. 32934 c.1200.---Henry de Pinkeny succeeded his father c. 1178 and died between 1205 and 1209. [Description by Alan G. Thomas, from whom it was bought in November, 1974]."
- [Grant of Wardship under the Great Seal of Elizabeth, giving Anne Sherard of Gaddesby (Leicester County) the "custodium corporis & martiagium" of her son Philip Sherard.], 13 April 1597 -; 1 leaf 20 x 32 cm. (Box 2)
  Done at Westminster.
  On vellum, large initial E with penwork deocration.
  Attached Great Seal of Elizabeth in darkened white wax, 14.5 cm. in diameter, showing her robed and crowned
  Latin text
- Gt. Brit. Privy Council of Edward VI. warrant for payment for delivering prisoner., 24 February 1552 -; Autograph document signed 1 p. 30 cm. (Box 3)
  Title taken from spine
  Letter written by Edward VI's privy council ordering the payment of 4 marks to Walter Bulles and Richard Bartlett; at the bottom receipt of payment is acknowledged by Richard Bartlett.
  Accompanied by engraved portrait of the duke of Northumberland.
  Transcript of the document with commentary (2 pages) included.
- Indenture between the Dean and Chapter of the Cathedral Church of Wells and William Clark., 5 July 1606 -; Autograph document signed 2 p. 29 cm. (Box 3)
  Between the Dean and Chapter of the Cathedral Church of Wells on the one part and William Clerk of Wells on the other part.
  Clerk has paid the Dean and Chapter a certain sum of money, in exchange for which they have demised to him a certain piece of land, which is then more thoroughly described in terms of location.
  Written in secretary hand.
- Aylisham Wood Court rolls., 4 August 1651-6 August 1660 -; Autograph document 291 p. 30 cm. (Box 3)
  Vellum
  Bound in wallet-style
  Bookplate of John Towneley and of Rudolfi Gottfried.
  Pencil note on inside cover: "This ms. calendared among Towneley papers in HMC Fourth Report (1874), p. 410."
  Court records.
- License No. 19041 issued by the commissioners of His Majesty's Customs to the skiff Clench belonging to the brig Emerson of Newcastle, Henry Marshall, master, 1811, October 18; ADS 2 p. 32.5 cm.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchase. Charles Apfelbaum, Valley Stream, New York. Jan. 23, 1991.
  Scope and Contents
  Three illegible signatures
  Partly printed
  Has watermark
  Bears paper seal
  Verso: Certified statement by C. Welstead and J. Walsh at the port of London on 23 Oct 1811 that security has been paid by William Williams and others
- Sidmouth, Henry Addington, viscount, 1757-1844, statesman. License issued to Sanderson, Barclay and Sanderson, merchants of London, to import into the port of Lisbon from the United States a cargo of grain in any ship of the specified size, but not bearing the flag of France, notwithstanding "any hostilities that may exist between His Majesty" and the United States, 1812, September 15; ADS 1 p. 22.5 cm.
  Purchase. Charles Apfelbaum, Valley Stream, New York. Jan. 23 1991
  Partly printed by Eyre & Strahan, His Majesty's Printers (194)
  Paper seal, tied with blue ribbon
  Accompanied by an order from the Council Chamber at Whitehall, dated 15 Sept 1812, printed by Eyre & Strahan (188), that the license be granted
- Melville, Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd viscount, 1771-1851, 1st lord of the admiralty. License No. 24710 issued to the ship Volunteer of Workington, Joseph Ashley, master, to sail from Liverpool to Brazil without convoy, "provided they shall be armed and manned." By command of their Lordships: John Barrow, 1812, October 16; ADS 1 p. 32 cm.
  Purchased. Charles Apfelbaum, Valley Stream, New York. Jan. 23, 1991
  Paper seal
  Watermark: GOLDING & SNELGROVE 1811
  Proviso: that the ship keep company with the West India Convoy "so far as their course lie together"
  Appended to the License: Certified statement, partly printed, that on Nov. 14, 1812, Joseph Ashley produced the license to sail in the prescribed manner from the port of Liverpool
- Freehold conveyance., 18 November 1898 - (Box 3)
  Conveyance of freehold to the Mortgage & General Investment Company, Ltd.
- Gt. Brit. Laws, statutes, etc., 24 June 1700 -; 2 Leaves (Box 3)
  An Act for the more effectual punishment of vagrants and sending them whereby how they ought to be sent
  Watermark JB
- Document in Low French., Undated - (Box 3)
  Watermarked OM (MO?)
- Of Declarations., Undated - (Box 3)
  Watermark ILit
- [International treaties, 1648-1713], 18th century -; Bound manuscript 1 vol. (Box 4)
  Bound in vellum
  Summarizes and provides commentary on different international treaties and notes important items in different articles of each treaty
  Occasionally includes marginal glosses to the right of text
  Starts with "Treaty of Peace at Munster" (Spain and Holland, 1748)
  Only the recto side of the pages has writing on it
  No significant spatial differentiation between different treaties on page.
  Breaks off in mid-sentence with several leaves having been cut out of the book
- Indentures, 1805? (Ovflat 36)